{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man’s regent, Sophia Alekseyevna, listened to his meetings through a hole in his throne and led a revolt that forced this leader to disband the Streltsy. This man learned Dutch shipbuilding techniques on his “Great Embassy” tour of Europe. He reorganized the Table of Ranks to weaken the Boyars, and he taxed long beards as part of his reform efforts. For ten points, name this westernizing Russian tsar.",
      "answer": "Peter the Great or Peter I"
    },
    {
      "question": "This route was extensively used by the Peoria Party, a group of advocates for colonization. The Bartleson-Bidwell Group was among the first to use this route after leaving Fort Hall. This route branched off in Montana and Utah via the Bozeman and Mormon trails. An iconic Learning Company game named for this route often ends with the player dying of dysentery, a fate that befell many travelers that took this trail to the Willamette Valley. For ten points, name this trail that settlers used to reach the Pacific Northwest.",
      "answer": "Oregon Trail"
    },
    {
      "question": "This case’s outcome was slammed in Byron White’s dissent, who claimed it “fashions and announces a new constitutional right.” This case, in which Harry Blackmun cited a “compelling state interest” as necessary to regulate privacy, affirmed a trimester framework. The initially anonymous plaintiff in this case, Norma McCorvey, later became a pro-life activist. For ten points, name this 1973 Supreme Court case that legalized abortion.",
      "answer": "Roe v. Wade"
    },
    {
      "question": "This practice was banned by Lord Mansfield’s ruling in Somersett’s case, which found that it had never been legal in England and Wales. In Brazil, this institution was abolished when Princess Isabel signed the Golden Law. Juneteenth is a celebration of the end of this practice, and Maroons were people that escaped it. For ten points, name this institution that was ended in much of the United States by the Emancipation Proclamation.",
      "answer": "slavery"
    },
    {
      "question": "Samuel Davies, a prominent leader of one of these movements, worked predominantly with slaves and later became President of Princeton. A conflict in one of these movements centered on a rift between “New Lights” and “Old Lights.” Jonathan Edwards’ “Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God” sermon was delivered during the first of, for ten points, what periods of religious fervor across the United States in both the 1730s and the 19th century?",
      "answer": [
        "Great Awakenings",
        "either the First and/or Second Great Awakenings"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s son Ernak became the last ruler of his people after another of this man’s sons died at the Battle of Nedao. The foederati combined forces with Flavius Aetius and Theodoric to defeat this man at the Catalaunian Plains. In 452, Leo I successfully convinced this man to call off his invasion of Italy. The title Flagellum Dei was a epithet given to this man that translates to “Scourge of God.” For ten points, name this leader of the Huns.",
      "answer": "Attila the Hun"
    },
    {
      "question": "One politician with this last name campaigned with a giant steel ball that rolled 5,000 miles across the country. Slogans written on that ball noted that “Old Allegany [...] started the ball” for a politician of this last name who defeated the incumbent Martin Van Buren, and that “in ‘88 [...] we roll it on for Gallant Ben,” his grandson. For ten points, give this surname shared by Benjamin and William Henry, a pair of 19th century Presidents.",
      "answer": [
        "Harrison",
        "Benjamin and/or William Henry Harrison"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A composer from this country wrote a Rondo for Abdelazar that was used as the theme for a piece that taught instruments to children, A Young Person’s Guide to the Orchestra. Another musician from this country wrote the forty-voice motet Spem in Alium and the melody to a Fantasia by Ralph [RAFE] Vaughan Williams. Thomas Tallis and Henry Purcell, were from, for ten points, what country where the folk song “Greensleeves” was supposedly written by King Henry VIII?",
      "answer": [
        "England",
        "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland",
        "Great Britain"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Life under this leader is depicted in the opening chapters of the novel The Three-Body Problem. This leader’s wife wrote a series of Eight Model Dramas, including The Legend of the Red Lantern and The Red Detachment of Women. This ruler wrote that “Imperialism and All Reactionaries Are Paper Tigers” in a book of quotations. For ten points, name this author of the Little Red Book who instituted the Cultural Revolution in China.",
      "answer": [
        "Mao Zedong",
        "either underlined portion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, Native Americans established the regional capital of Tahlequah in a territory granted by the Treaty of New Echota. The Unassigned Lands were originally designated for Native Americans in this state, which was the destination of the Cherokees who migrated westward during the Trail of Tears. For ten points, name this state where eager participants in an 1889 land rush, called “Sooners,” snapped up land between Norman and Tulsa.",
      "answer": "Oklahoma"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Friar Diego Dur´an helped document the history of this civilization. In this empire’s capital, many invaders drowned while carrying gold during an attack by Eagle Warriors. A man who helped conquer this empire betrayed Diego Velasquez and was aided by La Malinche [mah-lin-chay]. Montezuma II ruled, for ten points, what empire that was conquered after Hern´an Cort´es arrived in Tenochtitlan in modern-day Mexico?",
        "answer": "Aztec Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Aztec Empire is known as this type of alliance, based on the number of city-states involved. In the 19th century, a South American war pitted Paraguay against an alliance of this type.",
        "answer": [
          "Triple Alliance",
          "descriptive answers relating to 3 allies"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, while employed by his mentor Frankie Yale, was wounded by Frank Gallucio, a man who later served as his bodyguard. A group that investigated this man was chosen to be incorruptible by Eliot Ness; that group was disbanded after this man was arrested for tax evasion. Bugs Moran’s men were killed in the St. Valentine’s Day Massacre on the probable orders of, for ten points, what Chicago mobster nicknamed “Scarface?”",
        "answer": "Alphonse “Al” Capone"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eliot Ness’ group of incorruptible agents that investigated Capone was given this nickname. Ness’ memoirs and their ensuing film and TV adaptations took this name.",
        "answer": "The Untouchables"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This philosopher became disillusioned with his former employer after watching him get distracted by eighty dancing girls at his court. This man’s concept of ren, or humaneness, exemplifies itself as compassion in the just man and society. A series of “Four Books” espousing this man’s thought was compiled by Zhu Xi [j-oo she] during the 1100s. This man’s sayings are collected in works such as the Analects. For ten points, name this ancient Chinese philosopher.",
        "answer": [
          "Confucius",
          "Kong Zi"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Confucianism was one of this many apocryphal “schools of thought” that flourished during the Spring and Autumn and Warring States periods. A 1956 political liberalization movement in China called for letting this many “flowers bloom.”",
        "answer": [
          "100",
          "one hundred"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A national park in this state filled with fairy chimneys, or “hoodoos,” is named for settler Ebenezer Bryce. In 2002, an Olympic torch relay passed under the Delicate Arch in this state’s Arches National Park. This US state is the only one to have a majority of its population belonging to a single church. For ten points, name this Western U.S. state where, in 1847, Brigham Young founded Salt Lake City.",
        "answer": "Utah"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This politician and former presidential candidate oversaw the aforementioned 2002 Winter Olympics in Salt Lake City.",
        "answer": "Willard “Mitt” Romney"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This organization’s popularity declined after one of its leaders, DC Stephenson, was found guilty of the murder of Madge Oberholtzer. Mary Phagan’s murder inspired a resurrection of this group, which had been suppressed by Ulysses Grant’s Force Acts. This group’s first revival took place at Stone Mountain, where its members adopted clothing inspired by the film Birth of a Nation and burned a cross. For ten points, name this American terrorist white supremacist group.",
        "answer": "Ku Klux Klan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Confederate general was a prominent early leader of the KKK. During the Civil War, this man’s troops massacred surrendering black Union troops in the Fort Pillow Massacre.",
        "answer": "Nathan Bedford Forrest"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "David Lloyd George and this man were the “Terrible Twins” of the People’s Budget. Harry Truman invited this man to speak at Westminster College, where he discussed the “sinews of peace” and described postwar Europe as being split by an “iron curtain.” This politician promised his people his “blood, toil, tears, and sweat” in his first speech as British Prime Minister. For ten points, name this leader of the UK during World War II.",
        "answer": "Sir Winston Leonard Spencer Churchill"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Churchill replaced what fellow Conservative, who promised “peace for our time” after signing the Munich Agreement, as Prime Minister?",
        "answer": "Neville Chamberlain"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nearly 10,000 people died in this sea when the Wilhelm Gustloff was sunk. In 1994, bad weather on this sea sank a cruise ferry, killing over 800 people. Ships heading west out of this sea pass through the heavily crowded Kattegat and Skagerrak. The Gulfs of Bothnia and Finland are arms of, for ten points, what European sea northeast of Germany that names the set of three countries on its eastern shore: Estonia, Latvia, and Lithuania?",
        "answer": "Baltic Sea"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The MS Estonia ferry sank shortly after leaving this port city, the capital of Estonia, on its way to Stockholm.",
        "answer": "Tallinn"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1478, a member of this family named Giuliano was stabbed 19 times during High Mass as part of a failed coup d’etat. This family’s coat of arms features six spheres called palle on a gold shield. Popes Clement VII and Leo X were members of this family, which was targeted by the aforementioned Pazzi Conspiracy. Michelangelo and Donatello were patronized by members of, for ten points, what powerful Italian family that included Cosimo and Lorenzo the Magnificent?",
        "answer": "Medici family or the House of Medici"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Medici family dominated 15th century politics in this Italian city-state. Giuliano was killed in Il Duomo, this city’s cathedral.",
        "answer": "Florence"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Manhattan Project",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Weapons that were developed by the Manhattan Project.",
          "answer": [
            "nuclear weapons",
            "atomic bombs",
            "similar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German scientist who developed the theories of relativity and convinced FDR to start the Manhattan Project.",
          "answer": "Albert Einstein"
        },
        {
          "question": "Material used by the Manhattan Project to power its weapons, supplemented by the more readily available plutonium.",
          "answer": "uranium"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname of the weapon used to attack Hiroshima.",
          "answer": "Little Boy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last name of the husband and wife who were convicted of spying on the project for the Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "Julius and Ethel Rosenbergs"
        },
        {
          "question": "July 16, 1945 event in which “the Gadget” was tested, the first detonation of the Manhattan Project’s weaponry.",
          "answer": "Trinity test"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scientist who headed the project and quoted the Bhagavad Gita while observing the aforementioned test.",
          "answer": "J. Robert Oppenheimer"
        },
        {
          "question": "National lab in New Mexico where the project was headquartered.",
          "answer": "Los Alamos National Laboratory"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ireland",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city of Ireland, originally founded by the Vikings.",
          "answer": "Dublin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname inspired by Ireland’s exceptionally green meadows and plains.",
          "answer": "Emerald Isle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Branch of Christianity followed by the majority of Irish citizens and a minority of Northern Irish citizens.",
          "answer": "Roman Catholicism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious holiday during which the 1916 Irish rebellion took place.",
          "answer": [
            "Easter",
            "Easter Rising, Easter Rebellion, etc.",
            "Easter Week and any specific day mentioned with Easter"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pro-Irish independence political party associated with the Provisional IRA and led by Gerry Adams.",
          "answer": "Sinn Fein , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern Irish city where the Shankill Butchers killed two dozen civilians.",
          "answer": "Belfast"
        },
        {
          "question": "National theater, which burned down in 1951 and broke out in riots during The Playboy of the Western World and The Plough and the Stars.",
          "answer": "Abbey Theater"
        },
        {
          "question": "Irish political post, analogous to Prime Minister, that is currently held by Leo Varadkar.",
          "answer": "Taoiseach , but be lenient"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Antarctica",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Central Antarctic location where longitude is meaningless.",
          "answer": "Geographic South Pole"
        },
        {
          "question": "Protective layer of the atmosphere in which a hole is open over Antarctica.",
          "answer": "ozone layer"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose sightseeing Flight 901 crashed into Mount Erebus in 1979, having taken off from Auckland.",
          "answer": "New Zealand"
        },
        {
          "question": "flight.",
          "answer": "Sir Edmund Hillary"
        },
        {
          "question": "British explorer who died in 1912 leading the Terra Nova expedition.",
          "answer": "Robert Falcon Scott"
        },
        {
          "question": "Norwegian explorer whose team beat the British Terra Nova party to their objective and survived the return journey.",
          "answer": "Roald Amundsen"
        },
        {
          "question": "British explorer whose failed mission on the Endurance, incredibly, resulted in no deaths.",
          "answer": "Sir Ernest Shackleton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian research station where the coldest temperature on Earth was recorded. Its name means “East.”",
          "answer": "Vostok Station"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country set up the Company of One Hundred Associates in 1627 to expand its empire, and it relied mostly on runners of the woods to expand its trading networks. Those trading networks were contested between this colonial power’s (20 pts)",
        "Huron allies and its rivals’ Iroquois partners in the Beaver Wars. One of this country’s writers dismissed its (10 pts)",
        "North American holdings as “a few acres of snow” in Candide. For ten points, name this country whose loss on the Plains of Abraham cost it much of North America, including Quebec."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of France"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This President was in office during the passage of the Formosa Resolution, which promised U.S. protection of Taiwan and ended the First Taiwan Strait Crisis. This President’s administration was heavily lobbied by the United (20 pts)",
        "Fruit Company and orchestrated a coup against Jacobo Arbenz in Guatemala. Gary Powers’ U-2 spy plane crashed in (10 pts)",
        "1960, near the end of this man’s second term in office. For ten points, name this US President who served as Commander of Allied Forces in World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Dwight David “Ike” Eisenhower"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man names a thesis with Alonzo Church that concerns functions computable by one of his hypothetical namesake machines. Computers capable of mimicking human (20 pts)",
        "speech are said to “pass” a test named for this man, who worked at Bletchley Park during World War II. In 2014, Queen Elizabeth II announced an official (10 pts)",
        "pardon of, for ten points, what British mathematician who led the effort to decode the Enigma machine and who committed suicide following his conviction of homosexuality?"
      ],
      "answer": "Alan Turing"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2013, after campaigning on support for this issue, the Social Democratic Party refused to support a bill brought by Die Linke [dee link-uh] because it threatened the SDP’s coalition with the Christian Democrats. In 2017, over 160 million dollars was budgeted for a non-binding (20 pts)",
        "postal survey on this issue in Australia. Taiwan may soon become the first Asian country to adopt this policy, which, despite (10 pts)",
        "Angela Merkel having voted against it, became law in Germany in 2017. For ten points, name this form of matrimony."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "same-sex marriage or gay marriage",
        "equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Opposition leaders in this country include Merera Gudina of the Oromo People’s Congress. A leader of this country spoke to the League of Nations in 1936, condemning (20 pts)",
        "Italy’s use of chemical weapons against his people; that leader was ousted by the communist Derg in 1974 and is revered in Rastafarianism. (10 pts)",
        "Eritrea gained its independence from this country in 1993, two decades after the overthrow of Haile [”highly”] Selassie. Coffee originated in, for ten points, what east African country ruled from Addis Ababa?"
      ],
      "answer": "Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Leland Stanford sponsored a study of these animals that Eadweard Muybridge [”edward my-bridge”] used photography to undertake. Frederic Remington sculpted a bronze figurine of a (20 pts)",
        "“buster” on one of these animals. A sculpture with a nickname translating to “Honeycat” shows Erasmo da Narni on one of these animals, and was based on an earlier statue of the (10 pts)",
        "emperor Marcus Aurelius on military campaign. For ten points, name these animals which are typically featured with famous riders in equestrian statues."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "horses",
        "Bronco Buster"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An admiral from this country daringly sailed up the Thames to wreak havoc during the Raid on the Medway. Roving privateers from this country called the Sea Beggars captured Brielle [BREEL] from the (20 pts)",
        "Spanish in 1572, a turning point of the Eighty Years’ War. This country’s navy was led by admirals like Maarten Tromp and Michiel de Ruyter and supported by letters of marque issued by (10 pts)",
        "William the Silent. Indonesia was long ruled by an East India Company from, for ten points, what European maritime power ruled by the House of Orange?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "the Netherlands",
        "the Dutch Republic",
        "the Dutch Federation",
        "the Republic of the Seven United Netherlands",
        "the Kingdom of the Netherlands"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Many years after this battle, Henry Dearborn sparked a public controversy by publishing a critique of his commanding officer’s actions during it. A John Trumbull painting depicts Joseph Warren’s (20 pts)",
        "death during this battle. Forces led by William Prescott and Israel Putnam rebuffed a British attack at this battle. The order “Don’t (10 pts)",
        "fire until you see the whites of their eyes” was probably given at, for ten points, what 1775 battle, mostly fought on Breed’s Hill outside Boston?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Bunker Hill",
        "Battle of Breed’s Hill before mentioned"
      ]
    }
  ]
}